Guide to the Mark Straus Papers and Photographs ALBA.277
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mark Straus Papers and Photographs
1927-1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Straus, Raphael
Straus, Mark, 1909-1993
ALBA.277
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Mark Straus (1909-1993) was a Jewish doctor and who served with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War. After graduating from the University of Alabama he moved to Paris and received his medical degree from the University of Paris in 1936. A radical leftist, Straus went to Spain as part of the American Medical Bureau, Group IV, which arrived there in May 1937. Initially in charge of the Washington Battalion's medical unit, he went on to become chief medical officer for the 15th International Brigade. At the request of the Medical Bureau he returned to the U.S. on the S.S. Aquitania on July 12, 1938. The collection consists chiefly of correspondence and photographs documenting Mark Straus's life before and during the Spanish Civil War. Some additional material relating to his brother and fellow physician Bernard Straus is also included.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library
Harry Randall: Fifteenth International Brigade Photograph Collection (ALBA PHOTO 011)
Edward K. Barsky Papers (ALBA 125)
Historical/Biographical Note
Mark Straus (1909-1993) was a Jewish doctor and a captain in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. After graduating from the University of Alabama he moved to Paris and received his medical degree from the University of Paris in 1936. A radical leftist, Straus went to Spain as part of the American Medical Bureau, Group IV, which arrived there in May 1937. Initially in charge of the Washington Battalion's medical unit, he went on to became chief medical officer for the 15th International Brigade. At the request of the Medical Bureau he returned to the U.S. on the S.S. Aquitania on July 12, 1938.
After the war, Straus succeeded Dr. Edward Barsky as chairman of the Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee, when Barsky was sent to prison for refusing to cooperate with the House Committee on Un-American Activities in 1950. Straus taught at New York Medical College and at Flower and Fifth Avenue Hospitals and later had a private practice in Brooklyn, NY. He held another medical position as a consultant to the Fur Dressers and Dyers Joint Board, conducting research on the occupational hazards of dyes.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Spanish Civil War Correspondence, 1937-1938.
Series II: Subject Files, 1928-1938.
Series III: Photographs, 1927-1938.
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Provenance
The Mark Straus Papers and Photographs were donated to the Tamiment Library by Mark Straus's grandson Raphael Straus in 2009.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence and photographs documenting Mark Straus's life before and during the Spanish Civil War. Some additional material relating to his brother and fellow physician Bernard Straus is also included.
Series I: Spanish Civil War Correspondence, 1937-1938 contains letters written by Straus to his family during the war, as well as a letter from his father that Straus sent back to be preserved.
Series II: Subject Files, 1928-1938 mostly chronicles Straus's time in France as a medical student (roughly 1931-1936), with a few earlier and later items. The bulk of the material is correspondence, much of it in French. There is some correspondence relating to Straus's attempt to join the Naval Air Service and United States Army Air Corps partway through his undergraduate studies at the University of Alabama.
Series III: Photographs, 1927-1938 consists mostly of photographs of Mark Straus and others before and during the Spanish Civil War. A set of dental x-rays of his brother, Bernard Straus is also included.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Photographs.; Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Veterans.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Medical care.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, Jewish.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Straus, Raphael; Straus, Bernard; Straus, Mark, 1909-1993; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Spanish Civil War Correspondence, 1937-1938
  - Straus, H. (father): Letter to Mark Straus, [late 1937/early 1938] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Straus, Mark: Letter to Bernard and Pearl Straus about the Death of Lieutenant Daniel Hunter, Sep 8, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Straus, Mark: Letter to Bernard, Leon, Pearl, and Evelyn Straus, Jul 23, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Straus, Mark: Letter to Bernard Straus, Feb 19, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Straus, Mark: Letter to Leon Straus, May 25, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Straus, Mark: Letters to His Parents, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Straus, Mark: Letters to His Parents, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1928-1938
  - Brown, William S. (New Masses): Letter Returning Mark Straus's Translation of "The Two Processions" by Victor Marguerite, Jan 31, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between Neighbors "44" and "45" [Mark Straus] (partly in French), [circa early 1930s] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Brochart, E. to Mark Straus (in French), May 9, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Denny, George H. (President, University of Alabama) to Mark Straus, Jun 1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Fragments (partly in French), 1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Fromageau, Cherese (?) to Mark Straus (in French), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Fromageau, Cherese (?) to Mark Straus (in French), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Judith (?) to Mark Straus, Nov 23, 1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Schwartz, Leo B. to Bernard Straus, Feb 26, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Stalker, Marge to Mark Straus, Jan 2, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Straus, H. to Mark Straus (party in Yiddish), Jan 31, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Straus, Mark to Ida [?] and Ruth [?], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Straus, Mark (writing as Richard M. Straus) Seeking Admission to the Naval Air Service and the United States Army Air Corps, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Straus, Pearl to Bernard Straus, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Medical Notes (one includes drawing of two women on the reverse), [circa early 1930s] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Poem, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Student Identification: Mark Straus, Faculte de Medecine, Universite de Montpellier, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Study of the Love Behavior of Women" by Mark Straus, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Union Federale des Etudiants: Card Advertising a Program on "la Litterature Proletarienne Allemande" (with speakers Ilya Ehrenberg, Anna Seghers, Gustav Regler, et al.), [1934?] (Box 1, Folder 25a)
- Series III: Photographs, 1927-1938
  - Groups (including Mark Straus), Jul 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Medical Subjects (France): Printed Photos of Patients with Leg Deformations (?), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Negatives (I): Individuals and Groups (New York?), [1930s?] (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Negatives (II): Individuals and Groups (New York?), [1930s?] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Portraits: Mark Straus, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Portraits: Unidentified Woman [Judith?], 1927, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Spanish Civil War: Mark Straus, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Spanish Civil War: Mark Straus in Uniform (copy print), circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Spanish Civil War: Mark Straus with Major Robert Merriman (Chief of Staff, 15th International Brigade), Oct 1938 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Spanish Civil War: Mark Straus with Other Volunteers, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Straus, Bernard: Dental X-Rays, circa Mar 1937 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Straus, Mark with Unidentified Man (France), [1930s] (Box 1, Folder 37)